Guide to the Marguerite Moreno Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marguerite Moreno papers
1882-1949
1914-1948
GEN MSS 701
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.72
(7 boxes) + 1 portfolio
The Marguerite Moreno Papers consist of letters from Moreno to Gaston Baheux, an animateur of Parisian cabarets known as Tonton de Montmartre; other correspondence; journals, drafts of published writings, and unidentified writings; family photographs, photographs of Moreno, and theater and film production photographs of her and other actors; and a small amount of personal papers. The papers mainly concern Moreno's friendships and acting career, particularly during the 1930s-1940s, and her autobiographical writings, with some materials relating to her experiences as an acting teacher in Argentina and as a nurse during World War I.
Moreno, Marguerite, 1871-1948
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Autographes Demarest on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Marguerite Moreno (1871-1948)
Marguerite Moreno was a French theater and film actor. Born Lucie Marie Marguerite Monceau, she adopted her mother's name at the beginning of her career. Moreno was associated with Stéphane Mallarmé and the symbolist movement, and she was a member of the Comédie-Française, 1890-1903. During the 1890s she met the writer Colette, who became a friend and confidant. During 1908-1913, she taught at the conservatory in Buenos Aires, Argentina. Moreno served as a nurse in France during World War I, 1914-1915. By 1915 she was acting in films, and continued working in theater and film through the end of her life. In 1945, she performed the title role in Jean Giraudoux's La Folle de Chaillot.
Moreno was married to actors Marcel Schwob, 1900-1905, and Jean Daragon, 1908-1923. In the 1920s, she acquired La Source bleue, her home in Touzac (Lot), where she lived with her nephew and companion Pierre Bouyou, an actor who adopted the name Pierre Moreno.
Scope and Contents
The Marguerite Moreno Papers consist of letters from Moreno to Gaston Baheux, an animateur of Parisian cabarets known as Tonton de Montmartre; other correspondence; journals, drafts of published writings, and unidentified writings; family photographs, photographs of Moreno, and theater and film production photographs of her and other actors; and a small amount of personal papers. The papers mainly concern Moreno's friendships and acting career, particularly during the 1930s-1940s, and her autobiographical writings, with some materials relating to her experiences as an acting teacher in Argentina and as a nurse during World War I.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Correspondence, 1890-1949, undated. II. Writings, 1914-1915, undated. III. Photographs, 1892-1946, undated. IV. Other Papers, 1882-1948, undated.
Actors -- France; Motion pictures, French; Nurses -- France -- Diaries; Silent films -- France; Theater -- Argentina; Theater -- France; World War, 1914-1918 -- Medical care -- France; World War, 1914-1918 -- Personal narratives, French; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, French; Argentina -- Social life and customs; Lot (France); Diaries -- France -- 20th Century; Film stills -- France -- 20th Century; Photographs -- France -- 20th Century; Actors -- France -- 20th Century; Baheux, Gaston, 1897-1966; Daragon, Jean; Morand, Eugène, 1855?-1930; Moreno, Marguerite, 1871-1948; Moreno, Pierre; Printemps, Yvonne, 1894-1977; Schwob, Marcel, 1867-1905; Théâtre de la ville (Paris, France)
- Correspondence, 1890-1949, undated; Series I; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, followed by third party correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Most correspondence consists of letters from Moreno to Gaston Baheux. Circa 450 letters to Baheux are present, concerning their friendship, Moreno's work in theater and films during the 1930s-1940s, and other subjects including Colette, Moreno's home, in Touzac, her relationship with Pierre Moreno and his wife Micheline Moreno, and experiences during World War II.
  Other correspondence includes letters to Moreno from Eugène Morand, concerning performances of Hamlet in a French translation by Morand and Marcel Schwob.
  - A-Z general, 1890-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Baheux, Gaston, 1932-1940 April (Box 1, Folder 3-16)
  - Baheux, Gaston, 1940 May-1944 June (Box 2, Folder 17-30)
  - Baheux, Gaston, 1944 July-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 31-40)
    Includes letter from Pierre Moreno to Baheux, announcing the death of Marguerite Moreno
  - Morand, Eugène, 1904-1927 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Moreno, Pierre (letters from third parties), 1923-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Schwob, Marcel (letters from third parties), 1900-1905 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Other third party correspondence, [1899?]-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Writings, 1914-1915, undated; Series II; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Series II, Writings, is arranged alphabetically by title or genre, followed by unidentified writings and writings of others.
  Three published autobiographical works are represented by holograph drafts: Le bonhomme de neige, Origines du coeur, and Le statue de sel. Holograph drafts are also present for several short stories, as well as unidentified writings, and fragments. Journals for 1914-1915 document Moreno's nursing work in a military hospital in Nice. Writings of others consist mostly of unidentified poems and play fragments.
  - Le bonhomme de neige, undated (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
  - Journals, 1914-1915, undated (Box 4, Folder 47-51)
    Includes materials removed from journals
  - Origines du coeur, undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Le statue de sel, undated (Box 4, Folder 53-55)
  - Short stories, undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Unidentified, about Marcel Proust, undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Unidentified, about Victor Hugo, undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Other unidentified, undated (Box 5, Folder 59-64)
  - Writings of others, undated (Box 5, Folder 65-67)
- Photographs, 1892-1946, undated; Series III; 0.63; (1.5 boxes)
  Series III, Photographs, is arranged by subject.
  Photographs of Marguerite Moreno include portraits, theater and film production photographs, and family and other informal photographs. Theater and film production photographs consist of photographs of theater performances, film stills, and publicity images of Moreno and other actors, most unidentified.
  - Moreno, Marguerite
    - Portraits and informal photographs, 1932-1945, undated (Box 6, Folder 68-71)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Other Papers/Passport and other identification
    - Theater and film production photographs, 1939-1945, undated (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Photographs of drawings and paintings of Moreno, 1946, undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
      Includes one original painting by an unidentified artist
    - With unidentified people, undated (Box 6, Folder 74-75)
  - Other people
    - A-Z general, 1902-1946, undated (Box 6, Folder 76-77)
      Includes Eddie Cantor, Constant Coquelin, [Edmond Rostand?], Jean-Dominique Van Caulaert, and groups with Marguerite Moreno
    - Daragon, Jean, undated (Box 6, Folder 78)
      Includes theater and film production photographs
      Includes groups with unidentified people
    - Monceau family, 1892-1895, undated (Box 6, Folder 79-80)
      Includes Moreno's parents, her brothers, and groups with Marguerite Moreno
    - Moreno, Pierre, 1930-1946, undated (Box 6, Folder 81-82)
      Includes Micheline Moreno, other family members, and groups with Marguerite Moreno and unidentified people
    - Printemps, Yvonne, undated (Box 6, Folder 83)
      Includes groups with Marguerite Moreno and Jean Daragon
    - Schwob, Marcel, undated (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Unidentified
      - Theater and film production photographs, 1908-1945, undated (Box 6–7)
        Includes groups with Marguerite Moreno, Jean Daragon, Pierre Moreno
      - Other photographs, 1908-1910, undated (Box 7, Folder 94-96)
  - Places
    - Argentina, undated (Box 7, Folder 97)
      Includes Marguerite Moreno and unidentified people
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 7, Folder 98)
- Other Papers, 1882-1948, undated; Series IV; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Series IV, Other Papers, is arranged by type of material.
  Materials include a scrapbook of clippings about performances by Moreno and André Paysan in Argentina, 1911; a few family legal documents; and drafts and correspondence concerning an unrealized project for management of the Théâtre Sarah Bernhardt, proposed by Moreno and Edmond Roze in 1923. Also present are several contracts for theater performances concerning Moreno, Marcel Schwob, Sarah Bernhardt, and Sacha Guitry; correspondence about other contracts is filed in the Correspondence Series.
  - Clippings, 1911, undated (Box 7, Folder 99)
  - Contracts, 1901-1948, undated (Box 7, Folder 100)
  - Other legal documents, 1882, [18--] (Box 7, Folder 101)
  - Passport and other identification, 1921-1946 (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Theater programs, 1940, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Théâtre Sarah Bernhardt project, 1921-1923, undated (Box 7, Folder 104-105)
- Oversize, (1 portfolio)
  - Writings/Writing of others, undated (Box Port, Folder 106)
  - Photographs/Unidentified/Other people, undated (Box Port, Folder 107)